Guide to the Robert Swanton Platt Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert Swanton Platt papers
1913-1960
1913-1919
MS 1675
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(3 boxes, 1 folio)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, and memorabilia relating to Robert Swanton Platt's travels in Russia and China, and his teaching career with Yale-in-China.
Platt, Robert S. (Robert Swanton), 1891-1964
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert S. Platt, Jr., 1994. Gift of Nancy G. Platt, 2006.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Swanton Platt was born in Columbus, Ohio, on December 4, 1891. He graduated from Yale University in 1914. Platt taught at the Yale Collegiate School in Changsha, China, until 1915. Platt then entered the University of Chicago and obtained his Ph.D. in 1920
Platt served in World War I as a Captain in the 82nd Infantry and in World War II with the State Department and as Chief of the Map Division at the Library of Congress. Upon discharge from the service in 1918, Platt joined the faculty of the University of Chicago and taught until his retirement in 1957 as chairman of the geography department.
Platt, recognized as an expert on Latin America, had served as past president of the Association of American Geographers and as editor of its official publication, Annals, until his death on March 1, 1964.
Taken from: Yale Alumni Magazine, 1964 May.
Scope and Contents
The Robert S. Platt Papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, and memorabilia which pertain to Platt's travels in Russia and China and to his teaching experiences (1914-1915) at the Yale-in-China School (Ya-li), a college and hospital in Changsha, China.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Missions -- China; China -- Description and travel; Russia -- Description and travel; Platt, Robert S. (Robert Swanton), 1891-1964; Yale-in-China Association
- Inventory
  - Incoming correspondence
    - A-H, 1914-1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Ambulance Field Service, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chuan, S. J., 1914-1916, 1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hwang Ngan, 1916-1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hume, Edward and Charlotte, 1914, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - J-N, 1914-1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Kewley", 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Platt, Joseph (brother) Platt, "Rud" (brother), 1914-1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Platt, Maryette (mother), 1914-1917 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Platt, Rutherford H. (father), 1914-1917 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Platt, Rutherford H.: correspondence to family members other than R. S. Platt, 1913, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - R-W, unidentified, 1914-1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Werner, Adeline, 1914, 1915 August 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Outgoing correspondence
    - Hotchkiss School, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Platt family members, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Werner, Marguerite, 1914 August-1915 May, undated (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
  - Typescript of correspondence of Marguerite Werner to R. S. Platt (edited by R. S. Platt), 1914 August 4-1915 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - "A Journey Through Russia and Siberia - from Stockholm to Mukden": annotated typescript draft/typescript based on selected correspondence from R. S. Platt to Marguerite Werner [possibly edited by Rutherford H. Platt], 1914 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Writings
    - "How it Strikes the Newcomer," "Two Brothers Would A-traveling Go," "A Letter from an Old Boy, in China": articles by Robert S. Platt, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "My Religious Exposure," by R. S. Platt, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "A Day at Yale-in-China," by [R.S. Platt?], [1914-1915] (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Subject files
    - Bible stories (in Chinese), undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Business/calling cards, 1914-1915, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Chinese novels, elementary textbook, Circa 1914 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Finances: receipts, 1914-1917, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Miscellanea, 1914-1917, n.d (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1915, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Notes, fragments, 1914-1915, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Personal papers, documents, 1899-1916 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Playbills, programs invitations, 1915-1916, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Postcards, blank, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Travel ephemera, 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Travel papers, visas (Russian, language), 1914 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Yale Alumni Weekly: correspondence from Chinese students to editor (in English), 1915 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Yale-in-China: fund raising, 1916, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Yale-in-China: maps, floor plans, list of staff, printed material, 1914-1916 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Yale-in-China: student papers, 1915, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Photographs
    - Individually numbered photographs (#1-128) primarily of Yale-in-China with accompanying descriptions, duplicates, negatives, 1913-1915 (Box 3, Folder 42-48)
    - Photograph album presented to R. S. Platt at Christmas by students, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Photographs of R. S. Platt and staff and students of Yale-in-China, [1914-1916] (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Chinese family, unidentified, [ca. 1914-1915] (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - FOLIO
    - Poster depicting health regimens (Chinese language) (Box 4)
- Additional Material, 1914-1915; Accession 1995-M-089; 0.25; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Addition inventory by Carol King Jan 1995
  Received from: Robert S. Platt, Jr., 1994 Nov 18
  - "The Letters of Robert Swanton Platt to Miss Marguerite Werner" (written while travelling across Russia into China and while teaching at the Ya-Li School in Changsha, China); edited by McClellan Platt-Reynolds, 1914-1915 (Box 1)